welcome to meditating the genre waking
I'm a cognitive psychologist on a
cognitive scientists at the University
of Toronto where I academically teach
and scientifically study mindfulness
unrelated phenomena such as Insight flow
mystical experience transformative
experience higher states of
consciousness the cultivation of wisdom
and the aspiration to enlightenment the
enhancement of meaning in life I've also
been practicing the past the meditation
meta contemplation Tai Chi Chuan Qigong
as an integrated and dynamically a lot
of the ecology of practices for over 29
years and teaching it for close to 20
years welcome if you join us for the
first time this is actually a
progressive course and the introductory
course is done we're now doing advanced
techniques you're welcome to stay but I
recommend doing the following in the
description for this video you'll find
links to previous lessons go and
immediately do the first lesson you can
continue meeting with us but go and
immediately to the first lesson and then
every Saturday or Sunday do like lesson
2 lesson 3 lesson 4 and you'll catch up
with us so on Mondays and we meet every
weekday from Monday to Friday from 9:30
to 10:00 and sometimes a little bit
beyond 10:00 when there's extra teaching
or extra Q&A Mondays and our special
days we alternate on Mondays for 1 week
it'll be a dharma day in which I teach a
new principle or practice that builds on
previous principles and practices and
then the following Monday will be a PI a
day in which I go through the entire
sequence of practices all of the cheat
on the sitting Alexio Davina etc and we
keep alternating thusly going forward
every day we sit together and at the end
of every set Monday through Friday we
have a Q&A please keep your questions in
that Q&A to this ecology of practices of
that this this course that were on
together for more encompassing broader
questions please come to my monthly live
stream to YouTube QA it's at 3 p.m.
Eastern Time
it's june 19th of this month it's the
third Friday of every month so things
you can do to help me please like this
stream to increase its visibility so
that I can reach as many people as
possible and help as many people as
possible we can help as many people as
possible alright I think that's
everything I need to mention in terms of
the introduction yes so let's get
yourself in you know basic posture
please put your phones on do not disturb
and we will begin when I say begin begin
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can dating to great leisure
cultivated in your practice if your
everyday consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
all right so we have time for maybe one
question the reason what I'm going to
say only one question is I want to
answer this question in depth both to
answer the question trinsic ly to answer
the question but also extrinsic ly to
afford what we're going to be doing
later when we go through the wisdom of
Hypatia
course together so let's say seminar
welcome again Aleksey by the way as says
I can focus one of the pasta but
struggling and meta keep drifting away
into conversation with whoever I bring
up anyway to make it easier yes I'm
gonna recommend and this is non-buddhist
I'm not gonna be drawing upon the stoic
tradition stoicism which as I said we
will come back to and it's more and more
deeply the wisdom to Hypatia
I'm gonna recommend a practice from
stoicism that is an alternative way to
get to a place where you can exercise
meta that has good cognitive science
behind it it's based on control level
theory as I said I'll unpack that much
later in greater detail and this is the
practice of the view from above and so
what you do is obviously you find your
core for right and then you see yourself
as you are like you might imagine Utley
not in might not not imaginary but
imagine alee right you're in this riff
I'm in this room first-person
perspective and then I imagine myself
above this building looking down on this
body then I rise up higher and I see the
City of Toronto that's where I am that
Kobuk
and I see the comment
and I see the whole earth I'm gonna cool
back
I started get a sense of the universe as
a whole I'm seeing the earth within that
context and I also host open up time not
just this present moment the deep past
all the lives that have been lived
before all the creatures all the
organisms all the events inanimate and
animate now feel how that changes the
sense of self and sense of world a
process of Co identification and now
direct meta towards it the reciprocal
opening you've opened up to the morning
it's already been happening you've
opened up to the mourners of the world
perhaps initially yourself seems a son
but there was something in yourself not
your ego something in yourself that was
able to respond there was a more earnest
in you that could respond to that that
could be in that that was cyclical
opening that meta the mourners of the
world the more nests of yourself and do
meta they're direct meta towards all
being all beings all and all being
so try that as a different way of
getting into meta because it takes you
out of the direct interpersonal
situation that as you said often
triggers conversations interpersonal
emotions are specific socio-cultural
roles I still think the other meta is a
very important practice that's why I
taught it to you but the view from above
practice is independently powerful and
is a different way of getting into meta
I'm much more extensive kind of meta and
really emphasizing the reciprocal
opening that's at the heart of the
Buddhist form of meta so try that as I
said like I said I'm going to recommend
it to all of us later as we do the
wisdom of Hypatia of course but this is
an alternative way of getting into meta
that doesn't launch you immediately into
all of the tapes of the conversations
and the narratives in fact this is a
post narrative way of getting into meta
and so that might be helpful to you
Aleksey I think it's helpful to all of
us and it gives you a sense of some of
the Sapientia practices the wisdom
practices from within the Western wisdom
tradition that we need to rehome
ourselves within unfortunately I have to
end it for today there's so much more I
want to do right now but I want to thank
you for joining as always I want to
thank my dear friend and techno mage
Omar
my beloved son Jason is always there
behind the scenes please describe to
this video to be sort to this channel to
be notified of the next video on the
channel you will find the lecture series
awakening for the meaning crisis the
deal logos the discussion series the
dialogue series voices with reveille key
where these topics these ideas are
developed in depth and set into a much
more comprehensive an extensive
framework an entire philosophy a way of
life please invite others who might
benefit from sharing this series please
Brett is here my pleasure of doubt
there's people who on the discord server
have just participated in the serie in
the city though to some Alexio Davina
perhaps India logos I strongly encourage
you all to get involved with the discord
community there's a link in the
description to this video we will be
doing this every weekday morning at 9:30
Eastern Time
remember that continuity of practice is
more important than a quantity of
practice there is no enemy worse than
your own mind and body
there is no friend no ally no true
companion on the path better than your
own mind and body be lamps unto yourself
and to each other
take good care of one I'll see you
tomorrow